<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://io.italia.it/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://io.italia.it/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-03-13T17:49:42+00:00</updated><id>https://io.italia.it/</id><title type="html">{“it”=&amp;gt;”IO, il progetto per sviluppare l’app dei servizi pubblici”, “en”=&amp;gt;”IO, the project to develop the public services app.”}</title><subtitle>{&quot;it&quot;=&gt;&quot;Ricevi messaggi, avvisi, comunicazioni dalla Pubblica Amministrazione. Resta aggiornato sulle scadenze e paga tributi e servizi in un’unica app.&quot;, &quot;en&quot;=&gt;&quot;Receive messages, alerts and communications from all public entities, all within a single app.&quot;}</subtitle><entry xml:lang="en"><title type="html">Press release ForumPA 2018</title><link href="https://io.italia.it/2018/05/22/Press-release-ForumPA-2018.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Press release ForumPA 2018" /><published>2018-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://io.italia.it/2018/05/22/Press-release-ForumPA-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://io.italia.it/2018/05/22/Press-release-ForumPA-2018.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;io-the-project-to-develop-the-public-administration-services-app&quot;&gt;IO, the project to develop the public administration services app.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Digital Transformation Team at the Presidency of the Council of Ministers announces the launch of IO, a project to develop a public services app which will allow citizens to manage all their interactions with public administrations. A test phase  with a selected number of citizens and administrations is set to start this summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the project on &lt;a href=&quot;https://io.italia.it&quot;&gt;io.italia.it&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;#progettoIO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rome, 22nd May 2018 -  The Digital Transformation Team of the Presidency of the Council, in collaboration with AgID (Agenzia per l’Italia Digitale), announces &lt;em&gt;the birth of IO&lt;/em&gt;, a project &lt;em&gt;to develop an experimental application that will allow citizens to manage their interactions with the public administration and access public services directly from their smartphone&lt;/em&gt;. A preview of the prototype and details of the project are available on &lt;a href=&quot;https://io.italia.it&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;io.italia.it&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to the new app, every user can request and store documents and certificates, accept and make payments, as well as receive communications, messages and reminders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The app will make it possible to drastically reduce the time it takes to comply with public administration requirements,”&lt;/em&gt; affirms &lt;em&gt;Diego Piacentini&lt;/em&gt;, Special Commissioner for the implementation of the Digital Agenda. He continues, &lt;em&gt;“With this notification, payments and deadlines, operations that previously required a great deal of time, can now be completed in just few minutes.”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The application is not currently available in app stores, as the “closed beta” phase is scheduled to start any time soon&lt;/em&gt;. During the  summer 2018, some local and national services will also be provided through the app. In some territories, where the number and relevance of services are higher, we will invite citizens to take part in testing the application that will become part of their daily lives. With the increase in functions and services, the beta users numberwill gradually be expanded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;how-will-the-app-work&quot;&gt;How will the app work?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The app will be based on the integration of other systems already in place that will converge to facilitate citizens’ experience and the operation of the public administrations which will be able to use the functionalities of the IO platform to provide all of their services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“We are working on enabling platforms, whose components are necessary but not sufficient, to render the app fully operational,”&lt;/em&gt; explains &lt;em&gt;Diego Piacentini&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;“The unique ANPR (National Resident Population Register) will permit a synchronization of all citizen data that is currently scattered throughout some 8,000 different registers. SPID will guarantee a secure and unique means of access, whilst the PagoPA payment node will become the engine of the app’s digital purse.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-are-the-advantages-for-the-public-administrations&quot;&gt;What are the advantages for the Public Administrations?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IO starts from the analysis of the citizens’ needs yet offers an advantage for all public entities that provide digital services. Thanks to the integration of PagoPA, ANPR and SPID, the project makes most of the functions available which are already  common to all Public Administration services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“IO is an open project,”&lt;/em&gt; explains &lt;em&gt;Matteo De Santi&lt;/em&gt;, Manager for UX/UI &amp;amp; Product Design of the Digital Transformation Team. &lt;em&gt;“Any public entity can participate in the experiment, indeed, they are invited to do so. IO is designed with an open source logic, meaning the entire process of creating both the app and the infrastructure is completely public. Anyone can see how we are developing it and even lend a hand. Furthermore, the Digital Transformation Team is using technologies and methodologies that we hope will constitute best practices for all the digital services in Italy.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">IO, the project to develop the public administration services app. The Digital Transformation Team at the Presidency of the Council of Ministers announces the launch of IO, a project to develop a public services app which will allow citizens to manage all their interactions with public administrations. A test phase with a selected number of citizens and administrations is set to start this summer. Follow the project on io.italia.it - #progettoIO Rome, 22nd May 2018 - The Digital Transformation Team of the Presidency of the Council, in collaboration with AgID (Agenzia per l’Italia Digitale), announces the birth of IO, a project to develop an experimental application that will allow citizens to manage their interactions with the public administration and access public services directly from their smartphone. A preview of the prototype and details of the project are available on io.italia.it. Thanks to the new app, every user can request and store documents and certificates, accept and make payments, as well as receive communications, messages and reminders.</summary></entry><entry xml:lang="it"><title type="html">Comunicato stampa ForumPA 2018</title><link href="https://io.italia.it/2018/05/22/Comunicato-stampa-ForumPA-2018.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Comunicato stampa ForumPA 2018" /><published>2018-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-05-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://io.italia.it/2018/05/22/Comunicato-stampa-ForumPA-2018</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://io.italia.it/2018/05/22/Comunicato-stampa-ForumPA-2018.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;nasce-io-il-progetto-per-sviluppare-lapp-dei-servizi-pubblici&quot;&gt;Nasce IO, il progetto per sviluppare l’app dei servizi pubblici&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Il Team per la Trasformazione Digitale presso la Presidenza del Consiglio dei Ministri annuncia la nascita di IO, progetto per lo sviluppo della app dei servizi pubblici che consentirà al cittadino di gestire il rapporto con le Pubbliche Amministrazioni e che avvierà una fase di test con alcuni cittadini e alcune amministrazioni in estate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Segui il progetto su &lt;a href=&quot;https://io.italia.it&quot;&gt;io.italia.it&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;strong&gt;#progettoIO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roma, 22 maggio 2018 - Il Team per la Trasformazione Digitale della Presidenza del Consiglio, in collaborazione con AgID (Agenzia per l’Italia Digitale), annuncia &lt;em&gt;la nascita di IO&lt;/em&gt;, il progetto per lo sviluppo di un’applicazione sperimentale che permetterà ai cittadini di gestire direttamente dal proprio smartphone i rapporti con la Pubblica Amministrazione e l’accesso ai servizi pubblici. L’anteprima del prototipo e i dettagli del progetto sono disponibili su io.italia.it. Grazie alla nuova app, ogni utente potrà chiedere e conservare documenti e certificati, accettare ed effettuare pagamenti, ricevere comunicazioni, messaggi e promemoria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“L’app permetterà di ridurre drasticamente i tempi degli adempimenti del cittadino verso la Pubblica Amministrazione.”&lt;/em&gt; afferma &lt;strong&gt;Diego Piacentini&lt;/strong&gt;, Commissario Straordinario per l’attuazione dell’Agenda Digitale, che continua &lt;em&gt;“Con un sistema di notifiche, pagamenti e scadenze, in pochi minuti si potranno svolgere operazioni che prima richiedevano molto più tempo”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;L’applicazione non è attualmente presente negli app store e inizierà presto la fase di “closed beta”: infatti, a partire dall’estate 2018, alcuni servizi locali e nazionali verranno erogati anche attraverso l’app. In alcuni territori, quelli in cui il numero e l’importanza dei servizi saranno più alti, inviteremo i cittadini a partecipare al test dell’applicazione che entrerà così a far parte della loro vita quotidiana. Con l’aumento di funzioni e servizi sarà ampliato progressivamente il bacino di utenti della versione beta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;come-funzionerà-lapp&quot;&gt;Come funzionerà l’app?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;L’app si baserà sull’integrazione di altri sistemi già in funzione che convergeranno facilitando l’esperienza del cittadino e il lavoro delle pubbliche amministrazioni, le quali potranno usare le funzionalità della piattaforma IO per erogare tutti i propri servizi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Stiamo lavorando alle piattaforme abilitanti, quei componenti necessari, ma non sufficienti, per rendere l’app completamente operativa”&lt;/em&gt; spiega &lt;strong&gt;Diego Piacentini&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;“l’anagrafe unica ANPR permetterà di sincronizzare tutti i dati dei cittadini che a oggi sono sparsi in circa 8000 anagrafi diverse, SPID ne garantirà un accesso sicuro e unico, il nodo dei pagamenti PagoPA diventerà il motore del borsellino digitale dell’app”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;quali-vantaggi-per-le-pubbliche-amministrazioni&quot;&gt;Quali vantaggi per le Pubbliche Amministrazioni?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IO parte dall’analisi dalle necessità dei cittadini, ma costituisce un vantaggio anche per tutti i soggetti pubblici che erogano servizi digitali. Il progetto mette infatti a disposizione, anche grazie all’integrazione di PagoPA, ANPR e SPID, la maggior parte delle funzioni che sono comuni a tutti i servizi della Pubblica Amministrazione.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“IO è un progetto aperto”&lt;/em&gt; dice &lt;strong&gt;Matteo De Santi&lt;/strong&gt;, responsabile UX/UI &amp;amp; Product Design del Team per la Trasformazione Digitale, &lt;em&gt;“qualunque ente pubblico può partecipare alla sperimentazione, anzi, è invitato a farlo. IO è pensato con una logica open source, cioè tutto il processo di realizzazione sia della app che dell’infrastruttura è completamente pubblica, e chiunque può vedere come la stiamo portando avanti e darci una mano. Il Team per la Trasformazione Digitale, inoltre, sta utilizzando tecnologie e metodologie che ci auguriamo costituiscano delle best practices per tutti i servizi digitali del nostro Paese”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Nasce IO, il progetto per sviluppare l’app dei servizi pubblici Il Team per la Trasformazione Digitale presso la Presidenza del Consiglio dei Ministri annuncia la nascita di IO, progetto per lo sviluppo della app dei servizi pubblici che consentirà al cittadino di gestire il rapporto con le Pubbliche Amministrazioni e che avvierà una fase di test con alcuni cittadini e alcune amministrazioni in estate. Segui il progetto su io.italia.it - #progettoIO Roma, 22 maggio 2018 - Il Team per la Trasformazione Digitale della Presidenza del Consiglio, in collaborazione con AgID (Agenzia per l’Italia Digitale), annuncia la nascita di IO, il progetto per lo sviluppo di un’applicazione sperimentale che permetterà ai cittadini di gestire direttamente dal proprio smartphone i rapporti con la Pubblica Amministrazione e l’accesso ai servizi pubblici. L’anteprima del prototipo e i dettagli del progetto sono disponibili su io.italia.it. Grazie alla nuova app, ogni utente potrà chiedere e conservare documenti e certificati, accettare ed effettuare pagamenti, ricevere comunicazioni, messaggi e promemoria.</summary></entry></feed>